YUEYUE SHEN (沈越月)





RESEARCH INTERESTS

I'm a PhD student in astrophysics at the National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences (NAOC). My research interests are **Star Clusters**, **Stellar Spectroscopy**, **and Machine Learning**. My works apply **statistical inference**, **forward modeling** and machine learning to data from major surveys like **Gaia**, **LAMOST**, **and APOGEE**.

My current research focuses on star clusters, particularly on the properties of open clusters in the Milky Way, such as their initial mass function, structure, and dynamics. I also plan to extend my research to unresolved star clusters in nearby galaxies. Previously, I employed machine learning methods to measure stellar parameters from spectroscopic surveys.

EDUCATION

· National Astronomical Observatories of China (NAOC), CAS

2022 - Present

Ph.D. candidate, in Astrophysics. Mentor: Prof. Chao Liu

Beijing, China

Zhejiang University of Technology

2018 - 2022

Bachelor of Engineering, in Computer Science

Hangzhou, China

PUBLICATIONS

- **3. Yue-Yue Shen** et al., The Initial Mass Function of Young Open Clusters in the Solar Neighborhood, *in prep*
- **2. Yue-Yue Shen** and A-Li Luo, Distance and stellar parameter estimations of solar-like stars from the LAMOST spectroscopic survey, *A&A*, 691, A218 (2024)
- **1.** Bruno Sicardy et al. (incl. **Y.Y. Shen**), Constraints on the evolution of the Triton atmosphere from occultations: 1989–2022, *A&A*, 682, L24 (2024)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Mass Function of Open Clusters in the Milky Way from Gaia DR3

Jul 2023 - Present

Advisor: Prof. Chao Liu, Paper in preparation

- Isochrone fitting and Bayesian inference for the mass function of color-magnitude diagrams
- Cluster dynamics analysis and orbital integration
- Developed a Python package for cluster analysis STARCAT
- Distance and Stellar Parameter of solar-like stars from LAMOST

Mar 2022 - Sep 2024

Advisor: Prof. A-Li Luo, Paper published

- Use neural networks to derive stellar parameters and absolute magnitudes from spectra
- Spectroscopic distance of half a million stars in the LAMOST DR9
- Released open-source code SolarDis

ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

 Astrostatistics and Numerical Analysis Graduate course at UCAS, Prof. Chao Liu Sep 2024 - Dec 2024

Observing Experience

• 2.16m telescope at Xinglong Observatory, China Spectroscopic observations

6 nights, 2023 - 2024

• 0.7m telescope at Yanqi Lake Observatory, China

6 Oct 2022

Occultation light curve, contributed to Bruno Sicardy et al. 2024

SKILLS

- Programming and Computation: Python, C/C++, Java, SQL, HTML/CSS, LaTeX, Shell, Git
- Statistics and Machine Learning: Bayesian inference, Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC), Regression and Classification, Neural Networks and Deep Learning

AWARDS AND HONORS

• Excellent Student Prize of the University of Chinese Academy of Sciences 2024

 Academic Scholarship of Zhejiang University of Technology 2021